hello and welcome to this conversation
with Chris and this is actually a
continuation and a bit of a deviation
and convergence with the what we've been
doing together in terms of reading the
Platonic dialogues we're gonna switch
over and and take a sidetrack and read
on the way to language by Martin
Heidegger and the first chapter in that
book is a dialogue between basically
Heidegger and a student whose professor
was a student of Heidegger and so
this'll we'll be diving into it just
like we were reading the other dialogues
so Chris's he's gonna be the Japanese
person and I will be I'll be Heidegger
and then we'll read experience it and
then come to terms with what is what is
what is being released from the letters
if you so so to speak some few
housekeeping things
the art of circling the main thing that
I teach is from the circling Institute
is open for registration link for that
is below we have open weekends all of
this stuff is online now link for that
is below and we have drop-in evening
events every Thursday at 7 p.m.
California time
and you go to the Facebook page to see
all of that stuff and to the the website
page so all that's below if you're
interested in working one-on-one with me
and coaching both please email me my
emails for long
alright enjoy this was a his
conversation was so actually the
conversation was so fun and flowing and
revealing and there was that sense in
which we were taking at some point we we
started to something started to come to
salience for Chris and I and then we as
we started to talk about it we brought
in a lot of distinctions and ideas that
we've been already talking about and
kind of ran it like um went into dot
like bright in a dialectic and and I
think something is still kind of
wiggling wiggling out of like rolling
around in our heads that some so
interesting how
what we were thinking or what was being
thought in some way can be revealed
through taking up the thinking of
someone else
more of your own thought can be revealed
to you you know in this case basically
Plato platonic light through hired
through this dialogue with Heidegger
kind of running through that so it's
like it's it's interesting the the
fractal nature of all this go figure
welcome Chris thank you guy mmm-hmm so
happy to be on your screen yes happy to
find myself on yours right that so we're
taking a shall we say after having read
alkyl by T's now we're going to now read
a dialogue actually are rare in this
form dialogue with Heidegger and a I
believe it's I'm sure somebody will
probably correct me on this if it isn't
accurate but I believe it's it's a it's
a it's a it's a conversation that I
think actually happened the tiger went
back and rewrote but it's basically
between a a Japanese student of a
professor that was that that Heidegger
was a teacher of right so it's basically
like the Japanese student is of a
professor in Japan right of somebody
that who's his teacher was somebody that
Heidegger taught right and that's kind
of the basis of the conversation they're
in there talking so I think you'll be
the the Japanese student and I will be
he's just calls himself the Enquirer but
I think it's Heidegger you can think of
it as Heidegger okay yeah in in why I
wanted to do this was I'm not exactly
sure why I wanted to do this other than
it kind of called out however the I
think mostly I'm interested in just
engaging in this with you
given that we've been lucid ating dialo
goes in such a a platonic right from
Plato and Socrates and all that stuff it
just being really I thought it'd be
really interesting so whatever way it
contrasts and thus elucidates right this
the Platonic dialogues mhm yeah because
we're used to reading in the manner of
Socrates yeah and I think we're probably
gonna start again reading in the manner
of Socrates but I imagine that as we get
further and further along we're gonna
find that the manner changes right and
that actually it's been Socrates
speaking the whole time this for me this
is about as cold as a Reed gets have not
read this in advance so this will be fun
okay right apologies in advance for all
the a lot of the shoddy Japanese
pronunciations I'm about to utter yeah
me too okay
you know count Suzaku key he studied
with you you for a number of years count
Kikuchi has a lasting place in my memory
he died too early
his teacher Nishida wrote his epitaph
for over a year he worked on his on the
supreme tribute to his pupil I am happy
to have photographs of cuckoo keys grave
and of the growth in which it lies yes I
know the temple garden in Kyoto many of
my friends often joined me to visit the
tomb there the garden was established
toward the end of the 12th century by
the priests Honan on the eastern hill of
what was then the imperial city of kyoto
as a place for reflection and deep
meditation and so the temple grove
remains the fitting place for him who
died early hmm all his reflection was
devoted to what the Japanese call a key
in my dialogue with cuckoo key I never
had more than a distant inkling of what
word says okay pause right there so it's
interesting
I almost said miss redditors means but
he says that that word says I'm decided
so I want to highlight that because I
think that there's it's interesting to
think about when we speak of what a word
says versus what a word means hmm right
I think there's a that it shows a
disposition towards the word that's
different then yeah right yeah Sheila
French the with the French called the
difference between long and patrol the
the utterance as opposed to the the the
linguistic token of the speech as
opposed to its utterance something like
that yeah yeah later after his return
from Europe count cookie gave lectures
in Kyoto on the aesthetics of Japanese
art and poetry these lectures have come
out as a book in the book he attempts to
consider the nature of Japanese art with
the help of European aesthetics but in
such an attempt may we turn to
aesthetics why not
the name aesthetics you know what it
what it names grows out of European
thinking out of philosophy consequently
aesthetic consideration must ultimately
remain alien to the East Asian thinking
you are right no doubt yet we Japanese
have to call on aesthetics to aid us
with what aesthetics furnishes us with
the concepts to grasp what is of concern
to us as art and poetry you need
concepts presumably yes because since
the encounter with the European thinking
there has come to light a certain
incapacity in our language in what way
it lacks the delimiting power to
represent objects related in an
unequivocal order above and below each
other do you seriously regard this cook
in capacity as a deficiency of your
language considering that the encounter
of the East Asian with the European
world has become inescapable your
question certainly calls for searching
reflection here you are touching on a
controversial question which I often
discuss with often just often discussed
with count kooky the question whether it
is necessary and insightful for Easter
Easterners East Asians to chase after
the European conceptual systems in the
face of modern technical technical
ization and industrialization of every
continent there would seem to be no
escape any longer you speak cautiously
you say would seem indeed for the
possibility still always remains that
scene from the point of view of our East
Asian existence the technical rule which
sweeps us along must confine itself to
surface matters and that that for this
reason a true encounter with European
existence is still not taking place in
spite of all assimilation and Inter
mixtures perhaps cannot take place can
we assert this so unconditionally I
would be the last to venture it else I
should not have come to Germany but I
have a constant sense of danger with
count cookie to could obviously not
overcome what danger are you thinking of
that we will let ourselves be led astray
by the wealth of concepts which the
spirit of the European languages has in
store and will look
down upon what claims our existence as
on something that is vague and amorphous
yet a far greater danger threatens it
concerns both of us it is all the more
menacing just by being more
inconspicuous how the danger is
threatening from a region where we do
not suspect it and which is yet
precisely the region where we would have
to experience it you have then
experienced it already otherwise you
could not point it out I am far from
having experienced the danger to its
full extent but I have sensed it in my
dialogues with count cookie so so so
right there I just what I like I just
want to highlight something so here we
are there's this danger and we're like I
can get this sense of like we're walking
around like we're walk talking about
this danger but we don't know yet what
the dangerous in fact in fact there's
even this kind of move where he says
like he's like well I I've lived it but
I haven't really lived it right so I
just there's there's this way in which
the dialogue I get this sense of like
we're we're walking around that
something right but to name it there is
a sense in which there's it seems like
there's a sensibility that it wouldn't
be appropriate
it wouldn't be revealing and naming it
right which may be actually the pointing
to the danger that he's talking about
right I get weak so before we started
recording you and I were just talking
about something very similar weren't we
we were talking about the the
nominalization or d nominalization of a
world yeah that one kind of slinks into
unknowingly
and can become enveloped by
like it and in a dream and like as in a
dream and inculcated by without without
being aware of it and that waking up
from such a dream becomes really the
project of wisdom at least in the
Socratic tradition and there's we you
and I you and I spoke of the dangers of
being unable to wake up from such a
dream and how diello goes as a practice
is a way of augmenting the dream so as
to wake up in it
lucidly and then begin to probe it right
in that and almost like young sense of
active imagination so we were talking
about all of this before we actually
started reading and how such a dream can
become a world view that attunes your
normativity without without you
realizing that that's precisely what's
happening to you right when everything
you are doing when all of your behavior
begins to presuppose it at what point
did it become your presupposition and
that is a like it's a deep deep
existential danger that we were talking
about and I'm not I don't want to
presume that that's exactly what's being
referred to here but there is an
interesting little there's something a
bit synchronistic about the fact that we
were just talking about the dangers the
dangers of a world that becomes
axiomatic beneath your attention and
then constitutes your attention right
exactly right yeah and so and that being
the basis of ideology and ideological
thinking is that which guides your
attention being being unframed bull with
your attention and that being a great
danger right yeah and you were also
talking about this and it's it's a it it
you're also talking about when you're
you kind of wake up within a dream and
it's a lucid dream that you're talking
about this boundless freedom that
becomes of you but also this delicacy of
you could easily fall too far forward
and lose track that you're dreaming
or you're too self-conscious right like
and you bring a wake-up there's that
spell this sweet spot and we kind of
talked about that like I think I
referenced the the sense of you know
symbolically that sense that who is it
the theologian the modern theologian we
talk about Tillich yeah tiller you know
says the human being is the tension
between participation and individuation
situation that's right so I hear the
echoes in that here so just interesting
like this sense of this sense of a an
awareness of that there's something to
be respected right yet we must
participate with it in such a way that
we don't we don't insert right and wake
up from it right yeah right and we don't
just get lost in it so it's like almost
like the the the the struck perhaps the
structure of the conversation is
demonstrating that but it's also what
they're talking about
that's right so it's very much that's
interesting it's very much that same
thing we're thinking about her it might
be it might be it might be tight I think
it's not taught time and further reading
will tell but yeah I can't help but
notice the resemblance at least at this
moment yeah totally well if it's not
then we can definitely say Heidegger
didn't think of it you know I'll let you
see that right exactly
okay where were we to see I I'll just
you I'll just start oh okay did you
speak with it with him about it
no the danger arose from the dialogues
themselves in that they were dialogues I
do not understand what you mean
our dialogues were not formal scholarly
discussions whenever oh I'm sorry we
swapped without realize okay
I thought that that walk was funny
let's just start from the top that's a
top of the page you mean right yeah yeah
yeah okay that's good idea see we'll see
what you mean about flipping into a
different world and not realizing it
right away yes absolutely you have then
experienced it already otherwise you
could not point it out I am far from
having experienced the danger to its
full extent but I have sensed it in my
dialogues with count count cooky did you
speak with him about it no the danger
arose from the dialogues themselves in
that they were dialogues I do not
understand what you mean our dialogue
were not formal scholarly district
discussions whenever that sort of thing
seemed to be taking place as in the
seminars count cookie remained silent
the dialogues of which I am taught I am
thinking came about at my heart my house
like a spontaneous great game how cooky
occasionally brought his wife along who
then or festive Japanese garments they
made the eastern world more luminously
present and the danger of our dialogues
became more clearly visible interesting
how that is interesting I still do not
understand what you mean the danger of
our dialogues was hidden in the language
itself not in what we discussed nor in
the way in which we tried to do
but count cookie had uncommon ly good
command of German and a French and
English did he not sorry might might
write your fill out I'll take the line
again but pound cookie had uncommon ly
good command a German and a French and
English
did he not of course he could say in
European languages
whatever was under discussion but we
were discussing a key I it's just for
people watching us is pronounced hurts
it spelled I ki I key and here it was I
to whom the spirit of the Japanese
language remained closed as it is to
this day the languages of the dialogue
shifted everything into European yet the
dialogue tried to say the essential
nature of East Asian art and poetry now
I am beginning to understand better
where you smell the danger the language
of the dialogue constantly destroyed the
possibility of saying what the dialogue
was about some time ago I called I
called language clumsily enough the
house of being if banned by virtue of
his language dwells within the claim and
call a being then we Europeans
presumably dwell in an entirely
different house than Eastern Asian man
assuming that the languages of the two
are not merely different but our other
in nature and radically so and so a
dialogue from house to house remains
nearly impossible
[Applause]
you are right to say nearly for still it
was a dialogue and I should think an
exciting one because count cookie and
the workshops he held with us at Kyoto
University came back again and again to
those dialogues with you most often it
happened when we pressed him in our
effort to understand more clearly the
reason that had prompted him at the time
to go to Germany and study with you your
book being in time had not had then not
yet been published but after the first
world war several Japanese professors
among them our revered professor Tanabe
went to HUS role in frayberg to study
phenomenology with him that is how my
compatriots came to know you in person
it was just as you said in those days I
and Herr Schlemmer slurs assistant
regularly once a week read her SLOS
first major work the logical
investigations with the gentleman from
Japan by that time the master himself no
longer held his work and very high
esteem it had been published around the
turn of the century but I had my own
reasons to prefer the logical
investigations for the purposes of an
introduction to phenomenology and the
master generously tolerated my choice
and I believe just for just for some
context I believe if I understand this
rate at some point her slur like totally
went into the like kind of making his
work circle around like a transcendental
subject right in his earlier work which
is what I think Heidegger was
referencing was was less so it was
before the the Cartesian transcendentals
kind of subject and that's kind of I
think was the break that he had with
with Ursula yeah in case they don't
that's yeah that's good context
at the time I believe it was in 1921 our
professors attended the class you gave
they brought a transcript of it back to
Japan the title if I'm not mistaken was
expression and appearance that in any
event was the title of the course yet
professor cooky must have had his
special reason for coming to me in Mara
burg Marburg indeed and I believe these
reasons traced back to that course whose
transcript was also much discussed
elsewhere in Japan transcripts are muddy
sources of course what is more the
course was most imperfect yet there was
quickening in it the attempt to walk a
path of which I did not know where it
would lead I knew only the most
immediate short range perspectives along
that path because they beckoned me
unceasingly while the horizon shifted
and darkened more than once I can
Patriots must indeed have sensed some of
that again and again it was said that
your questions circled around the
problem of language and of being in fact
this was not too difficult to discern
for as early as 1915 the title of my
dissertation does goddess doctrine that
done stunts Curtis Duns Scotus yes I was
saying it in the German doctrine of
categories and theory of meaning the two
perspectives came into view doctrine of
categories is the usual name of the
discussion of the being of beings theory
of meaning means the gramatica
speculative ax the metaphase
reflection on language in its relation
to being but all these relationships
were then still unclear to me which is
why you kept silent for 12 years and I
dedicated being in time which apparently
in 1927 to her soul her slur became
phenomenology because phenomenology
presented us with the possibility of a
way still it seems to me that the
fundamental theme language and being
stayed there in the background it did
stay there even in the course you
mentioned of 1921 the same held true
also of the question of poetry and of
art in those days of Expressionism these
realms were constantly before me but
ever more and already since my student
days before the first rule of war was
the poetic work of Holdren and Trek 'el
and still earlier during my last years
in the gymnasium to give a date in the
summer of 1907 I came up against the
question of being in the dissertation on
her slurs teachers friends
brentano its title is on the manifold
meaning of being according to Aristotle
it dates from 1862 the book came to me
as a gift from my fatherly friend and
fellows Swabian dr. Conroy Gruber later
to become Archbishop of fries burger
Fred Freiburg then he was Visser of
Trinity Church and Constance
do you still have the book here it is
for you to look at I'm sorry here it is
for you to look at and to read the
inscription which runs quote my first
guide through Greek philosophy in my
gymnasium days unquote I'm telling you
all this but not in order to give the
impression that I already knew then
everything I am still asking today but
perhaps there is confirmation here for
you who is a professor of German
literature love and know hold rooms work
particularly well of a phrase of that
poet which begins in the fourth stanza
of the hymn the rhyme for as you began
you will remain the quest of language
and of being is perhaps a gift of that
light ray which fell on you who would
have the audacity the claim that such a
gift has come to him I only know one
thing because reflection on language and
on being has determined my path of
thinking from early on
therefore discussion has stayed as far
as possible in the background the
fundamental flaw of the book being in
time is perhaps that I ventured forth
too far too early that's interesting you
know what's in what's interesting about
that are you I'm not sure I know
uh-huh yeah I know cuz I know it I mean
it's a it's a it's it's a it's the big
talk in kind of high daguerreian
philosophy things that I've heard a lot
which is where
it's presumed that Heidegger and you can
kind of get it here right where he's
basically saying no hiding like being in
time was kind of a mistake I started it
and I the very thing that I I was
attempting to transcend I presuppose in
transcending I got caught in the thing I
was trying to leave but my understanding
is is that since since his his whole
corpus is are a lot more of us of high
degrees writings which is like a hundred
twenty books basically an insane amount
of insane amount of writing you can
start to see people are starting to
speak of that no actually you can kind
of see that no it's it was it was not
his thought but being that turned right
that it was like you couldn't have you
know they call it like Heidegger number
one and Heidegger number two some people
right and he's like in Heidegger said
like look okay you can call it that but
as all as long as you can you can say
that Heidegger number two is predicated
on Heidegger number one and isn't is
contained within it and co contained
with each other right so it so much it's
much more rich and complex than than
just a mistake right mm-hmm right isn't
that if it anything it wasn't if you
want to look at it as a mistake it was a
necessary mistake that revealed right
the ground that he necessarily assumed
didn't notice that he was assuming was
there so such that when he stepped off
it he got to see that it wasn't there
and thus right right yeah so by somehow
by over transcribing the being of which
he wrote he realized that the work was
in identical with it yeah and so could
find his way back to it yep yep almost
ironically yep yeah
that's cool thank you for that little
sojourn into Heidegger guy you yeah that
was good I mean that's that's I mean
that is sojourn into the historical
Heidegger yeah lovely say that's what
we're doing yeah okay so why are you
going to start on on the top of page 8
oh right there we go
that can hardly be said of your thoughts
on language true less so for was all of
20 years after my doctoral dissertation
that I dare discuss in a class the
question of language it was at that same
time that I in class made public my
first interpretation of holdren things
in this in the summer semester of 1934 I
offered a lecture series under the title
logic in fact however it was a
reflection on the logos in which I was
trying to find the nature of language
yet it took nearly another 10 years
before I was able to say what I was
thinking ok I love that's a great
sleight of hand right I offered a
lecture series under the title logic in
fact however it was a rep it was a
reflection on the logos in which I was
trying to find the nature of language
it's it's almost like a hospital a nice
little philosophical bait-and-switch
the exact kind of bait and switch that
is revealing right right exactly of its
true topic yes it's like it's true about
this yeah it's that little turn of like
if you're in the dream right like that's
right little what about that over there
about that over there yeah that's right
that's right yeah
what does the dream really about what is
this what is the proper story of the
dream yeah yet it took nearly another
ten years before I was able to say what
I was thinking the fitting word is still
lack
even today the prospect of the thinking
that Labor's to answer to the nature of
language is still veiled in all its
vastness this is why I do not yet see
whether what I am trying to think of as
the nature of language is also adequate
for the nature of the eastern language
whether in the end which would also be
the beginning a nature of language can
reach the thinking experience a nature
which would also would offer the
reassure the read the the I'm sorry
would offer the assurance that European
or Western saying and Eastern saying
will enter into dialogue such that in it
they're seeing something that Wells up
from a single source they're seeing
something that Wells up from a single
source Hey
yeah it sounds like the melody of the
Geist that we often talk about totally
the melody of the Geist that emerges
from the pool of the logos when the
splashing participants turned still
right yeah yeah but a source that would
then still remain concealed from both
language worlds that is what I mean this
is why your visit is especially welcome
to me since you have already translated
into Japanese a few of Kleist's plays
and some of my lectures on Holdren do
you have a keener ear for the questions
that I address to your compatriots
almost 35 years ago
you must not overestimate my abilities
especially since I coming from Japanese
poetry still find it difficult to
respond to European poetry in a way that
does justice to its essential nature
even though the danger remains that it
necessarily implies in our using the
German language for our dialogue I
believe that I have meanwhile learned a
little more so that now I can ask
questions better than several decades
ago at the time at that time my
compatriots dialogues with you after
class were taking a different direction
therefore I now ask you what prompted
the Japanese professors and later in
particular count cooky to give special
attention to that transcript I can
report only of cookies explanations they
never did become fully clear to me for
in characterizing your manner of
thinking he often invoked the terms
hermeneutics or hermeneutic as far as I
can remember I first used those words in
a in a in a later course in the summer
of 1923 that was the time when I began
my first drafts of being in time in our
judgment count cookie did not succeed in
explaining the terms satisfactorily
neither concerning the meaning of the
word nor regarding the sense in which
you were speaking of a hermeneutic
phenomenology cookie merely stressed
constantly that the term was to indicate
a new direction of phenomenology it may
indeed have looked that way in fact
however I was concerned neither with a
direction in phenomenology nor indeed
with anything
knew quite the reverse I was trying to
think the nature of phenomenology in a
more original manner so as to fit it in
this way back into the place that is
proper its which is properly its own
within Western philosophy so something I
just want to point out here so like this
trick the struck me um indeed I knew
quite the reverse I was trying to think
the nature of phenomenology so again he
just he he doesn't say think about mmm
right but to think it right so there's
something I think I'm there's something
I you know if we look at the difference
between when I say think about the
nature of phenomenology or like think
differently or something right think
about it differently if I remove the
about and I say think phenomenology
right more originally or something what
am i what is the what what do you here
is the indication between the difference
between thinking about something and
thinking it I think one so it strikes me
intuitively is that one one is a form of
gnosis and one is not
right so you think of the plutonium
quote right the organ knowing is the
organ fitted to the object right when
they share identity well when they share
identity that's what we mean by gnosis
yeah so the the the relation to the
nature of phenomenology no no what am I
trying to say the nature the nature of
the relation between his thinking and
phenomenology is a relation that he
aspired to be one of gnosis yeah
something like that yeah so there's a
this way in which to think the nature of
phenomenology versus think about it the
about seems to have phenomenology
already kind of assumed as something
right upon which my thinking which would
kind of think about it as if it could
somehow stay the same without thinking
about it right like phenomenology can
stay there and thinking could stay there
and if they meet and discuss each other
fill they'll or not they'll still be the
same so I think what he's saying is like
to think it more originally right which
is has to do with origin right to think
it from origin right so in some way
there's this it's interesting why I'm
what I think why this is this is
speaking to me is I'm I'm uh
I've been reading something by johannes
teacher who's you know he's a he's a
Haida garyun scholar and in we were
talking we're going through
Heraclitus and breaking down they hear a
cleitus language in this very original
way but I'm noticing like the experience
feels like I start I start the sentence
and it just seems normal like okay I'm
understanding I'm understanding and then
by the end of the sentence I've somehow
I'm a different person that's right
that's right that's right
great yeah yeah yeah because there's
there's a because somehow the the
speaking becomes something of necessity
that transforms you in its likeness into
its likeness yes that's yeah that's it
yeah that's it yeah yeah exactly it's
like you're it's like you're Phil eiated
by it mm-hmm right it's like you become
you'd be come up you become it a species
of it right right and this is also
interesting because reading I would say
that in some ways reading is a lot more
like listening than listening is right
hmm because on some level that's
interesting because reading is like
reading is like overhearing I've been
thinking about that term except you
supply the voice to your author
that to be yeah yeah and so and so what
you're hearing is of yourself and not of
yourself some obviously yeah which is
really interesting but I also think it's
like very much the same thing in
dialogue because it's the same thing
what's the same that it's reading even
more so with reading whereas if you have
a thought right and you veer away from
while you're listening to me you'll
notice that you hadn't heard me right
but the moment you stop thinking is to
return to listening yeah
so there's wedded relationship right
between thoughts and listening right
yeah are one two are like really
one-to-one so on some level when we say
to think something on some level it's to
be deeply obedient to its origin right
like and some level to think it fully is
to think it as if it was being funk the
first time right there's there's no beat
like because I know harkening is related
to obedience in a and so in so listening
kind of OB yes so there's no obedience
and that goes back to the thing that you
were talking about with with gnosis
unlike oh so Oh to listen is to become
fitted to the organs of the object that
you're becoming and that is that
transformation and just mutual
disclosure yeah probably
it's like it's kind of like not to get
to mister
about it but it's kind of like a it's
like it's like it's like the kind of the
hypest the hypostatic read avow ring
that patinas talks about right that all
things eventually are sits in the way
that all things are read avowed by the
one when when they advert themselves to
it right right right
when right when when the child adverts
to its parent properly it calls itself
to the presence of its parent right and
is read avowed by it all right so when
we hear ourselves a spoken we hearken to
the originating speech something like
that that's why it really matters are
you getting out with Oh
does it ever it's a matter of it's it's
a matter of deepness necessity it
actually is yeah matter of deepest
deepest necessity who you what company
you keep yes a it's a it's a it's a
divine and existential choice right who
do I want to be devoured by totally
right yeah yeah Wow yeah who's going to
who's listening ear is going to tune me
to hearken to the deepest form of the
logos yeah that I can access right by
whose ear do what I want to listen I
think that's it
I think that's it it's by whose ear do I
want to listen right that's why I like
you talking to you right like yeah
because because when I listen by your
ear like the boundaries of the world
retreat away instantly it becomes deeper
it becomes its its flesh becomes far
more permeable right um immediately and
then so right that's that's when you say
what you here by my ear I hear myself
right in a way that I I couldn't just by
myself
somehow like yeah yeah yeah interesting
yeah but then that ear right we can as
we know we can then in trajector that
ear right right and
and keep it keep the the dialogic matrix
by which that ear is heard through to
keep that intact and to keep that
revolving right even when we're not
actually you know in actuality doing it
and I get the sense in this in this
dialogue like on some level I mean
Heidegger keeps kind of standing
something up and then kicking it away
right on every level of like what he of
both both of what he's currently saying
but also what he has says including what
he thought at that time that he was
doing he keeps standing something up and
hang it out standing it up and kicking
it out yeah right it yet yet there's
something present like at least in this
there's something gathering in this
right like there's a world on some level
that I can I can sense yeah yeah because
it's like it keeps pull you leading it
keeps it keeps it in erupts and then
it's almost like he retracts it back it
erupts niba tracks it back he's trying
to it's liked it's like it it's like an
exercise in optimal gripping I think
that way yeah right interesting he's
trying to grip the aboutness of the
dialogue through the dialogue and so the
dialogue is tuning itself as it as it as
it as it advances in the direction about
which it speaks it seems like the
optimal grip is to recognize it's not an
optimal grip right it's yeah yeah yeah
right it gets this right right well
because that yeah that the grip has to
be that the the the faulty grip has to
be disillusioned of its dis
disillusioned of its mastery before it
gains a grip again right yeah right
because because yeah cuz there's a way
it's interesting cuz that there's a way
when it reveals its non optimal grip
that very revealing is disclosing the
thing that you can then grip it's like
it's
it's saying not the great grip discloses
more of the right grip right and the
more it does that right you kind of get
this sense of yeah totally yeah all
right exactly exactly
I think we're but why did you use the
term I think that's you on Jeopardy
but why did you use the term hermeneutic
the answer is given in the introduction
to being in time section 7 C page
blahblah 58 but I will gladly add a few
remarks to dispel the illusion that the
use of the term is accidental I recall
that it was this illusion which caused
objections the term hermeneutics from
munetaka
was familiar to me from my theological
studies at that time I was particularly
agitated over the question of the
relation between the word of holy
scripture and theological speculative
thinking this relation between language
and being was the same one if you will
only it was veiled in inaccessible to me
so that through my deviation and false
starts I sought in vain for a guiding
thread I know too little of Christian
theology to comprehend what you refer to
but it is obvious that through your
background in your studies you are at
home and theology in a manner totally
different from those who come from
outside and merely pick up for reading a
few things that belong in that area
without this theological background I
should never have come upon the path of
thinking
but origin always comes to meet us from
the future
interesting haha take that line again
yeah
without this theological background I
should never have come upon the path of
thinking but origin always comes to meet
us from the future hmm that's like
that's bad that's like prolepsis mm-hmm
yeah if the to call to each other and
reflection makes its home within that
calling and thus becomes true presence
later on I meet the term her MuNet --ax
again in wilhelm dilthey in his theory
of the history of ideas tilth ease
familiarity with her mimetics
came from that same source his
theological studies and especially his
work on flame maker you know you were
saying something is coming to mind right
where isn't it we were talking about how
there's like the the Greek the ancient
Greek notion of the logos is the
gathering and then there's the the the
Brea Kenosha of the the proclaiming word
right or yeah yeah word of creation the
affective word yeah yeah and then you
said and Christianity on some level is
the is that is the marriage of the two
yeah yeah that's one thing that a 4-leaf
bowman points out is that in many ways
when when the word like the the word
that descends in the Holy Spirit is a
word combined of the gathering the
gathering and arranging unity of the
Greeks and the poesis of the Hebrews
something like that right so it's just
interesting to think about like okay so
Heidegger is the origin
speaks from the for the future and this
having to do with the Herbie eidetic
sense of reading the Bible right I'm
just I'm just kind of seeing if anything
pulls on you yeah yeah yeah yeah hi
there is something yes you could feel I
have to say yes yeah it's like this is
kind of sense of like on clothing right
yeah like they're in some strange way
that's the thing well that's the thing
my understanding of actually her
Dianetics in the get Marian sense right
who is a student of Heidegger I mean and
this is probably a way oversimplified
summary but I think what like he had
this the sense of that you know at some
level if you look at hermiod etics is
trying to find like trying to figure out
what the original author meant by his
utterance right what you found is that
what they found out is that you couldn't
actually do it in other words you
couldn't not bring back your like you
couldn't bring your own frame of you
couldn't not bring your own frame of
reference even in just getting rid of it
yeah he says I'm on that level from that
level people looked at that and said oh
so you can't do it it's a failure but
right but gadamer points out like no
that's exactly how history is made
that's right is that you is that you
look back right in some sense from the
history's position from the you cut out
from a guy can't hurt you anymore
still can't I guess I should make sure
that it's not my problem no yeah no yeah
so there there's you know there's
something about this diet this kind of
dialogue with that history and the
moment actually the creative movement of
history itself right is precisely in its
looking back having not being able to
like it won't release its frame but it
but it that's how you create the past
right and it's interesting because like
philosophical insights what personal
insights to always have that quality of
notice is that when it's an insight
right
usually there's well you know like this
the the sixth sense right he's dead
through the movie no one knows it and
then it's an the movie or like he sees
it on the corner of his eyes like whoa
and you recognize he's dead but the
moment you recognize it it goes back to
the very beginning of the movie to all
the main remakes and remakes the world
and it was it was obvious it was obvious
the whole time but unda stinked right so
to come into distinction right yeah
exactly
there's something about multiple levels
in which this is what they're talking
about I think is revealing itself
through the through what's being said
and also through the way it's going
about back and forth it being said
that's right that's right I mean I think
that that precise that is and is not
that precise dialectical tension that
you're talking about I think is what
what John's been trying to put his
finger on with inventio as a term right
the simultaneous discovery and creation
right it's that that that that concept
that that concept is has has has
something very much to do with
contracting the hermeneutic circle right
it's the it's the effective word that
brings about that which that which
already was and yet was and yet was not
to our site or something like that the
word isn't that isn't that spoken it
through the word inception which word so
when you realize or you reveal and both
create in your revealing right Oh like
the incepting of an idea yeah the I D
like the the incepting of an idea that
brings it forth into being
yeah yeah yeah yeah right yeah
yeah that's interesting yeah yeah
there's something there for sure all
right so we are okay so you are okay let
me just I'll start from the top right
here it developed first and formally in
conjunction with the interpretation of
the book of books the Bible there is a
lecture by ashley maker that a a
published that was published
posthumously by his manuscripts under
the title her mimetics and criticism
with special reference to the New
Testament I have it here and shall read
you the first two sentences from the
German introduction and here's the
German introduction Ruby nedick's and
criticism both Phyllis phonological
justice lepton disciplines both methyl
mythology's belong together because the
practice of each presupposes the other
the first
is in general the art of understanding
rightly another man's language
particularly his written language the
second the art of judging rightly the
genuineness of written works and
passages and to establish it on the
strength of adequate evidence and data
accordingly the word her Munich's
broadened and the appropriate sense can
mean the theory and methodology for
every kind of interpretation including
for example that of works of the visual
arts quite do you use the term in this
broad sense if I may say within the
style of your question I have to answer
in being in time the term hermeneutics
is used in a still broader sense broader
here meaning however not the mere
extension of the same meaning over still
larger area of application broader is to
say in keeping with that vastness in
keeping with that vastness which Springs
from the originally being keeping I say
that again
ok some of this is important being
exhaustible broader here meaning however
not the mere extension of the same
meaning over still larger area of
application broader is to say a keeping
with the vastness which Springs from
originally being in being in time
hermeneutics means neither the theory of
the art of interpretation nor
interpretation itself but rather the
attempt the attempt first of all to
define
the nature of interpretation on Chania
netic grounds take a second with that
one
yeah like that it took breathe it in and
just waiting to see if there's a next
sale but what does Hermia netic what
does hermeneutic mean then I do not have
the audacity to yield to the suspicion
which here suggests itself that you are
now using the word hermeneutic willfully
be that as it may what matters to me is
to hear from your own lips and if I may
say so authentic explanation of your use
of the word otherwise it will still not
become clear what moved conclude these
reflections so just interesting that
we're still we're still trying to get
clear on count Cooky's reflections about
heidegger's what Heidegger meant but I
do not understand Socrates right totally
exactly all right I shall be glad to do
as you ask only do not expect too much
for the matter is enigmatic
and perhaps we are not dealing with a
matter at all perhaps rather with a
process or with what is the case all
hyphens what or with what is the case
but much but such terms will click
quickly land us in inadequacies I want
to know what the German word for what is
the case is right
yeah but only if we already somehow have
in view what our saying would want to
reach its it again read that we're good
but only if we already somehow have in
view what our saying would want to reach
it can hardly have escaped you that in
my later writings I no longer employed
the term perm you nedick's ye are said
to have changed your standpoint
standpoint think about that word for a
second right yeah right the logos of a
given proposal creates a standpoint from
which to view and he's saying here the
the Japanese conversation partner but if
we only but if but if only we already
somehow have in view from our standpoint
what our saying would want to reach and
yet the saying the saying is creative of
the standpoint right or perhaps more
precisely the hearing of the saying yeah
the the the harkening of the saying is
constitutive of the standpoint right and
that's why the saying that's why the
staying is creative of the world that
provides a view to to the world beyond
the world if we can say to say that
right exactly right because every
they're changing their standpoints
constantly yeah totally yeah yeah that
thing it keeps knocking itself down
stands up on it proposes without which
it stands on to its heard beyond its own
stand which creates a new it knocks that
one off and puts you on a new stand
that's right yeah like the plinth to the
footstool yeah right the proposition
being the footstool from which to gain
the taiko scopic view yeah and and
that's that's the that's the that's
certainly the very Socratic view of the
word I would say that Heidegger seems to
be teasing out but his has poor
interlocutor isn't quite right his
exemplifying it without continent to it
I think you are said to have changed
your standpoint I have left in earlier
standpoint not in order to exchange it
for another one but because even the
former standpoint was merely a way
station along the way the lasting
element in thinking is the way in ways
of thinking holds within them that
mysterious quality is the mortis as ways
of thinking hold within them that
mysterious quality that we can we can
walk them forward and backward and that
indeed only the way back will lead us
forward obviously you do not mean
forward in the sense of in advance but I
have difficulty in finding the right
word for into that nearest nearness for
into that nearness nearest nearness
which we constantly rush ahead of and
which strikes us and strange each time
anew when we catch sight of it
I'm gonna take that again guys oh four
into that nearest nearness which we
constantly Russia Russia head of the
nearest nearest that nearest nearness
which we constantly rush ahead of and
which strikes us estranged each time a
new when we catch sight of it that
strikes me that that he's just given it
strikes me that that is such nests the
nearest nearness which we constantly
rush ahead of and which strikes us
estranged each time anew when we catch
sight of it I think that's what that is
yeah I think that's that is I think
that's such they're catching it anew in
in catching sight of it right on some
level what you caught is it will say the
suchness of you as it as it beams
through your face the the face what I
see is not changed but what animates it
animates the nature of what I was
already looking at but not seeing right
the suchness right yeah such this yeah
interesting okay
that nearest yeah I love that that
that's a beautiful turn of phrase the
nearest nearness which we constantly
rush ahead of because there's a way in
which that right the what we keep
talking about also with John that that
somehow the the more nests and you and
you and you pinned it before because you
were reading something that mysterious
quality we can walk that thinking of
hope okay sorry I'm jumping all over the
place I want to I want to take these
eyes forward I want to think I want yeah
exactly it does I think I just fall down
though when I try and go forward to back
because I just tripped yeah yeah so
there's these two passages so I want to
take one just slightly above that you
just read and then you stopped as you
read it because you you you too
Tech did the more nests so the lasting
element is thinking is the way and ways
of thinking hold within them the
mysterious quality that mysterious
quality that we can walk them forward
and backward so the mysterious quality
is that we can walk them forward and
backward okay and you said wow that's
like the morning which I think was it's
intuitively right yeah so then so then
the that quality that mysterious quality
that we can walk them forward and
backward and then and then let's take
the nearest nearness which we constantly
rush ahead of as the suchness and
there's a way in which the morning the
more nests because knowable well the
mornings available shall we say only
from within the sight of such nasaw
if we were to transcribe that into the
language of these passages it would be
sitting this is just from just playing
with this I have no idea what this with
what this lands at or not
but the the the mysterious quality that
we can walk the mysterious quality that
we can walk ways of thinking forward and
back that they are that they remain that
they remain suggestible by the
necessities of being is a mysterious
quality that we can only cotton to from
that nearest nearness which we
constantly rush ahead of and which
strikes us as strange each time anew
when we catch sight of it so the knowing
of the for that nearest nearness allows
us a view into that mysterious quality
that we can walk our thinking forward
and backward
which we constantly wish you had that
which we constantly rush ahead of it's
precisely what calls to presence that
quality that we can walk our thinking
forward and backward yeah yeah right
that the the espousal lives they be
espousal of the standpoint as such yeah
is what gives us a view to it's more
great right and there's something that
happens in taking the view right there's
some way in which in taking the view
we already rush ahead of it right
because it's already more than its
proposition and and it is that is it as
we is we rush ahead into the mortise
right
there's here's this forward and backward
thing of like the way there's something
about like the yeah uh-huh I was just
yeah just an image call to mind it's in
many ways it's a very obvious image
because it involves the canopy but it's
you know how when you're when you're
actually this is just a visual metaphor
but to me it says something it it's like
you know how when you're actually in
motion when you're walking when you're
rushing ahead of your nearest nearness
such as that it no longer becomes your
nearest nearest right when you're in
Moline ambulating around mm-hmm you know
on a walk
you can't let's say you it's at night
and you want to get a look at the Stars
we want to get a good look at the Stars
like not a glance you want to actually
look at the Stars such that you feel
enveloped by the canopy which only
actually happens if you stop plant
yourself right usually you have to
actually lie down on your back to get a
really really good survey right yeah but
it actually requires again think about
this idea of the nearest nearness
you actually have to assume your nearest
nearness you have to assume the identity
of your nearest nearness I'm thinking of
literally the ground beneath you wait
yes you have to assume the identity of
the nearest near near yeah you have to
assume the identity of the nearest
nearness yeah as it were the ground
beneath your feet in order to gain a
view to the morning which is already
which is always already overlooking mmm
whatever it is you're near yeah yeah
right so imagine you you have to lie on
the ground in order to gain a view to
the cosmos right doing it as you're
walking doesn't work you can't do it
right mmm and then you become like you
become like fail 'yes and you like fall
into a ditch i think it was it wasn't it
failed Daley's you fell into a ditch I
think it will um you become like
failures you fall into a ditch if you
try and gain you when you try and gain
perspective on the more without assuming
the identity of such and knowing it
again knowing it as gnosis sharing in
its identity without sharing on the
identity of such you can't actually gain
a view to more right so this so there's
also this quality like it strikes me as
you know and the the ancient way of
being oriented is precisely looking at
the Stars but like but once you get
situated with the Stars it tells you
where you are so that you can look right
where you are because if you do if
you're not oriented you don't know what
you're looking at you weren't anywhere
right that's right that's right so it
returns it returns it returns to situate
the tsardom the view to the more returns
to situate yourself as such yes right
that's right your nearest nearness right
Orient's it becomes place properly
lonely as beholden and
looked and overheard by the morning
against into which it into which it
echoes and against which it it is
distinguished yes yes and then there's
something about so now what presupposes
my orienting and even needing the Stars
is that I'm going somewhere right and
now there's that there's a going
somewhere that I've been before right
but then there's going to somewhere
where I've not been before right for
which actually I'm more apt to orient
myself into the Stars because think
about it it's like how do I know to go
somewhere where I haven't been before in
what way is it already present right to
even to pretend to pretend knowing about
it right mm-hmm so there's like yeah
yeah there's something about in that
prehension right because this is it's
interesting this is this is like this is
precisely why I think I was listening to
you know it's funny is trying to is
listening to a group of hacker
programmers try to try to encode this
thing that they can't they can't get it
the code to do which is how do you get
the computer to represent not knowing
what it doesn't know right or or but but
but but also not knowing but even more
than that which all that seems to be
predicated on in some levels how do you
get it to represent the domain of that
you know that you don't know right what
you don't know right there's like a
there's like a level of negation that's
that's that's the big I mean it seems to
be the big mystery vertigo yeah yeah
well in some level when we walk outside
there is the domain
in fact on some level it's got to be the
most orienting horizon I think if it's a
horizon um because there's a domain that
like I can plan for and then I can plan
for the things that I don't know about
but I can anticipate but then there's
the then there's that sense which I
can't even plan for but I know it's
there
question is is how do I represent it to
myself right which is that I think it's
maybe what the mortise is right is like
it's the morning as I have access
somehow to right that there's a beyond
that's disclosed itself as such as
somehow making presents the prehension
is upon which I would I would I know to
explore the exploration of which would
be that is the future development of my
own character my own suchness right
right right right right right it's like
so then the use of the word quad
language is like the call and the call
and response and the response of the
Sachin to the moor is always the such
against the moor in virtue of which it
becomes itself and becomes more right
becomes it's becoming itself properly
and dialectically is becoming both
itself as such and itself is more yeah
but only when raised against the canopy
of more nests if we can put it that way
only when raised against the canopy of
more nests and silhouette does the yes
well if we could even talk about the
self this way right does the self as
such is the self as such revealed in its
more nest
yeah and the logos right
you know it's funny I thought about this
funny enough this is like I think I
thought about this either while I was
stoned or after I was done being stoned
or something like that when I used to
get stoned a lot um was like that
there's that experience of you know like
of being stoned which i think is where
you have that thought right that as you
go along right like you're having the
most profound thought and then at some
point you go to reference back what you
were thinking about to bring it all
together and it's gone
great yeah there's that kind of quality
of like in it and I likened it to this
is like it's somehow normally right when
we have a thought the the are axioms the
presuppositions that that meant a lot
that makes possible for that thought to
be a thought follows the thought usually
it trails along behind it maybe
something like when you're stoned or
whatever that it somehow allows thoughts
to move forward right to move forward or
backward and the way that Heidegger is
described
yes and ahead of its Fiat like like a
couple of things like beyond away from
its own axioms and the further away it
gets from its own axioms the more
luminous right and other right it's
gonna become right beautifully at some
point it's interesting inch oh my god
it's gonna be like this and at some
point you have to actually look back
yeah right yeah and then like if it if
you look back and you can't remember
then you go you're back right access
right and you're just stoned right
that's right that's right
maybe enlightenment is this is it pulls
forward and then you look back and
instead of its sucking you back in
you're stoned
it's somehow pulls forward the axioms
were forward we are it be core or it
spatialize --is the tension yes yes in
the distance yes in the distance travels
which would be analogous to something
like I was thinking the axioms you get a
new bed
crowd that's given by the foreground
that's not the same axioms that's right
yes right that's wrong that's the
beautiful point guy that's so insightful
that and that and that well that's what
and that's part of why people pursue
altered states of consciousness speaking
just phenomenologically right because
because the turning of the foreground
into the background the trends did the
the the way that the way that the
transparency opacity shifting seems to
equilibrate in altered states of
consciousness is such that it they they
balance in such a way that they becomes
the world the the word and by the word I
mean the particular logo of the thinking
the logos of the thinking that
constitutes the frame of your experience
in the span of a moment has the quality
of translucence such that your that the
thinking as the thought occurs to you
the thought becomes the frame in virtue
of which the world presents to you the
whole world takes on the salience of a
particular mode or form of life
determined by the logos of that
originating thought right so that's why
you know when people are whether whether
you know stone or what not that that
that I don't know thinking cold seems to
affect cold hmm right or or or bring
like that that that that the occurrence
of the thought is an invoke a ting mana
that calls into presence its referent
and it calls it into presence more
acutely than I think a lot of people
feel in their regular sober states so
that the foreground of the thought turns
into the background of the world
seamlessly yes right total and that's
why that I mean and that's why it's so
phenomenally I mean that's why it's so
it's so that's why those states in
that's part of there's a lot of reasons
right but that's part of why those
states are so phenomenally attractive
is because they bring to present a form
of symbolic knowing which is not to say
that those forms of symbolic knowing are
somehow dependent upon those states or
that those states are of necessity
because I don't I don't think that's
true necessarily but but they are a way
understanding the body of symbolic
thinking and it's translucence because
you can understand how the foreground of
the word becomes the background of the
world and that that the tonus of the
relation between the word as spoken and
the world as realized and lived seems to
tighten I think in those states in that
state of translucence between
transparency and opacity now it's a
delicate thing right because I mean just
as just as waking within a dream and
trying to cultivate and hold together a
lucid state within a dream is a very
delicate thing and it's lost in a second
right it's lost in a second right like
the flow state because it is a flow
State right it's lost its as soon as you
become overly conscious of it it slips
it slips so you have to it's like you
have to you have to maintain an optimal
form of consciousness such that you're
attentive without being without
objectifying walls because it's a trans
ejected state anyway when you when you
talked about sort of the four grounding
in the background and the relation
between those two yeah
yeah that's a that's a great insight
it's coming to my I'm glad we're
recording this there's like a lot of
stuff that I'm probably gonna steal for
my my writing um not if I steal at first
he has totally I'll turn off the you
can't transcripts but the I was thinking
about like so so I think maybe this is
what Garret Oh was getting at are you
familiar at all with Garrity's science
and sophistication
his scientific work I'm not oh yeah he
was like into botany and all kinds of
the-- basically some people credit to
him of doing a different science garret
Oh was that that was a different that
polymaths drive me crazy I mean he just
used the architects him
yes hate him but one of the things he
did is he is he he somehow and I'm gonna
I'm gonna probably thought say this
correctly but something in the ballpark
of he said he said that so we we can
read like man-made objects right
cultural objects because we have the
corollary concept right that that allows
us to instead of seeing the desk right
instead instead of seeing a bunch of
wood and a bunch of shapes we see a desk
we're able to read it so they like that
the object is more like the letter in
which we read right and because we
behold on some level that the the
corollary concept right that allows us
to to have the the the the material
become transparent right to that thing
any and he said and this way it was
really interesting he's like but when we
look at nature we don't know how to read
it
we don't read it and he says the science
tries to understand the text of nature
by measuring the shape of the letters
but he I think he was seeking to think
the logos of nature oh wow right through
this process of intense observation in a
certain way where he wanted to think the
species right to read that the logo
right to read again through mind he had
this whole way of doing that and
tracking and this whole thing and
there's something here about like this
notion of salience of that in being able
to somehow see even the beginnings of
looking at you're like looking at your
your world your arena right in this way
of being able to begin to read something
like the eternal in more and more of the
arena right but ah yeah in is actually
like that and that's usually the sign
that you know when something's
transformed for somebody it's right it's
not this sense of this wreck it's not
usually the sense of like I'm my
subjectivity strikes me as different
it's more like the world says something
different my mother approves for me
different I noticed myself responding to
a world that what that I that I
responded to completely differently last
week that now right the sense of see
reading the world that the logo says in
the earth itself or in the world right
the shamanic the shamanic exercise yeah
yes the proto-germanic exercise isn't it
right yes of when the form of life when
the logo says the form of life of the
world becomes imminent imitable within
within your subjectivity then it's like
you extend the scope of your it's like
extending the scope of your design in
some sense isn't it yes yeah yes yeah as
well that's yeah and and that's why I
mean that's why those mimetic rituals
that's why those mimetic transformations
and performances are so crucial right
the symbolic performance of of imitating
the tiger or imitating the bird it is
flight or that kind of again there's all
those proto shamanic exercises that we
still have effected in our culture to
some degree affect those precise changes
wasn't that kind of what Corbin was in
some senses I always got this edge with
Corbin that we he like if you were to
fully realize the talos of his work it'd
be something like who is fully realized
how you would know is it to all the
world would occur as an icon right yeah
every everything has
translucence who are talking about
everything everything is an aperture
through which through which mourneth
shines and suchness reaches right right
something like that I think right yes
everything is some Zen site sandbox
iconic we think we're I'm certainly more
accustomed to using the word symbolic
but to mean very much the same thing
yeah right that that that the the the
boundaries of the canopy become
permeable again in such a way that that
that everything becomes a basis for
seeing everything becomes a standpoint
from which to know but but realized
first as a standpoint and then
secondarily as any kind of object yes
yes and their intention right there's
the prehension there's the preemption
and that and that's and that's that's
the way in which propositions right in
the Socratic tradition if we want to
draw it all the way back to Socrates
that every proposition and the Socratic
tradition is a standpoint from which to
see and know and and and it is that it
is that first every every every uttered
logos of knowing is its meaning of
meaning rather than its meaning because
every ever the logos of every
proposition reaches to its parent logos
reaches to the source to the source that
calls it to attention and there's the
way there is that kind of a Lang there's
that elongated stretch right yeah it's
interesting there's this cut there is
this kind of like yeah and that seems to
be well also the way of wisdom the sense
of like how do you start to become more
wise when you can't possess wisdom it's
like well it more informs the way that
even you're mistaken you're not knowing
is somehow the way in which will
disclose itself in the beginning in the
back and that somehow that it allows
this the landscape to come to say Li
in precisely the thing that's that you
don't have it's weird right right yeah
exactly exactly and then and then the
and then the the logos the organization
of any given proposal any given form of
speech becomes part of the way insofar
as it becomes in the way Heidegger means
it here a Waystation right it becomes a
way a a yeah
it becomes a a way safe a way station on
the quest for its or its higher order
its meta meeting becomes a way station
on the quest of its meta meaning it's so
interesting I'm kind of hearing John in
the background wandering at feasts like
if what he's would say is like well
we're talking about relevance
realization aren't we yes because that
would be that would be it it's because
what you're realizing is the the
relevance ends up being all the whole as
revealed in what's most relevant so what
does most salient is also what's most
relevant right that's right and that's
the threat right the closer and closer
and closer and closer right exactly
exactly and then each offering each
offering is simply a a a meaning that
provisions for more so interests and he
would certainly apply the the relevance
realization said quite rightly to that
because it's so interesting because you
can also so interesting to think about
this because there's a way that there's
an all this to something like
ideological possession that's like it's
interesting it's very similar right but
in this up but it's completely upside
down right of this trickery right of
utter salience of what saturated is
obvious that discloses a standpoint
which becomes self referential through
making what is most real not what's most
salient confirming itself becoming ever
ever ever more predictable yet enclosed
in and the moment it closes in is the
moment it starts becoming brittle
greatly like need exam or standpoint and
then you'll yeah exactly
a fleeing like like foaming like froth
of fighting for and against everybody
that's right that's right no no but but
when when the stamp when the standpoint
of such becomes confused with the
mortise it beholds and thus loses the
tension with the more nests that
envelops it and gives it its situation
then the traveler along the path has
lost the path right the way station has
lost the way
when it has confused itself first you
know the Tower of Babel something like
that right and and and its view to the
heavens the ground upon which its view
to the heavens is gained becomes
mistaken for the heavens views yeah
interesting and that I think is as you
say ideology yeah since yeah yeah so
interesting yeah very interesting
this is great I I think I met Mike I met
my neurological compass' capacities
without thought it was that mind like
two hours ago but here we are
yester you gave me and her energy I
didn't know I had
you always domestic fantastic mutual my
friend so we got we got pretty far into
Heidegger not bad not bad at all well
pick it back up we'll pick it back up
next week or something like that yeah
it's all about the way yeah
[Laughter]
all right look Fred talk to you later
talk to you later bye